Working Inventory of the Robert E. Marshak Papers, 1947-1990
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Working Inventory of the Robert E. Marshak Papers, 1947-1990
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1988-060
65.1 cu. ft. 65 boxes; 1 oversize folder
The collection consist of Marshak's files on the Shelter Island Conferences (1947-49) and his administrative and correspondence files on the Rochester Conferences on High-Energy Physics (1950-57), which he founded. The papers also includes correspondence, notes, reports, files, speech texts, newsclippings, autographs, photographs, transcripts, and other personalia donated in 1994--these materials are unprocessed.
Marshak, Robert Eugene, 1916-1992
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Robert E. Marshak Papers were acquired by the Special Collections Department of the Virginia Tech University Libraries in two separate donations. The first 5 cubic feet of materials (Boxes 1-5), also known as the Rochester Conference Papers, was given in 1989. These papers are primarily about the Rochester Conferences on High Energy Physics (1950-70), which involved thirty-five Nobel Prize winners, twenty-seven of whom were conference participants.
The second approximately 61 cubic feet of materials was given to Special Collections in 1994. It includes items such as correspondence, notes, reports, speeches, news clippings, photographs, and other personalia from Dr. Marshak's high school days in the 1920s to his death in 1992. This second donation is unprocessed.
The bulk of the papers pertaining to Dr. Marshak's term as President of the City College of New York are archived by the Hoover Institute on War, Revolution, and Peace at Stanford University.
Biographical Note
Robert E. Marshak was born in 1916 in the Bronx, a borough of New York City. Marshak's academic ability was recognized early, and despite their poverty, his family encouraged his studies. As a result, he finished James Monroe High School at the age of 15. From high school, he enrolled in the City College of New York (CCNY), a tuition-free university that served as an exit from poverty for generations of immigrants. After one semester at CCNY, he received a Pulitzer Scholarship which provided full tuition and a stipend which allowed him to continue his education at Columbia University. College appears to have been a profound intellectual experience for Marshak. He initially majored in philosophy and math, and served as the dance critic for the school newspaper. In his senior year, he switched to physics, and came into contact with Nobel Laureate I.I. Rabi. Rabi was initially skeptical of his commitment to physics, but later became a friend.
Marshak graduated from Columbia in 1936, and went to graduate school at Cornell University via a fellowship. At Cornell, he studied with Hans Bethe, who at the time was working on problems pertaining to energy production in stars, which later won Bethe a Nobel Prize. Marshak wrote his dissertation on energy production in white dwarf stars. His basic conclusion was confirmed about forty years later when the white dwarf orbiting Sirius came into view. He completed his Ph.D. degree in 1939 at the age of 22.
Jobs were hard to come by in the late 1930s, especially for Jewish scientists for whom positions were limited by quotas. Marshak nonetheless was able to get a one- year, non- renewable position at the University of Rochester. Here he met, among other notables, Victor Weiskopf, the future director of CERN, the nuclear accelerator facility in Geneva, Switzerland. During this time a tenure-track position opened in the Physics Department at Rochester which Marshak received.
Teaching at the University of Rochester was interrupted by the outbreak of World War II. Marshak became involved in the war effort, as did many scientists at the time. Initially, he worked on developing radar in Boston, Massachusetts, then on the British atomic bomb project in Montreal, Canada. In 1943, Marshak married Ruth Gup, a school teacher in Rochester. Later he joined the Manhattan Project which was developing the American atomic bomb in Los Alamos, New Mexico. At Los Alamos, Marshak was a deputy group leader in theoretical physics, a rank which allowed him to be privy to the overall strategy of atomic bomb creation.
After the war, Marshak returned to the University of Rochester, where he moved quickly through the ranks. He become a chair professor (the Harris chair) and the head of the physics department in the 1950s. He was very active as a researcher, and was a participant at the famous Shelter Island Conference where he proposed the two-meson theory. During his fourteen year chairmanship the Physics Department at Rochester became one of the top 10 in the country, and a recognized center for advanced research in physics.
During his years at the University of Rochester, Marshak became intensely interested in international science. He felt that scientific cooperation was an important first step in the quest for global peace. In 1956, he was a member of the first delegation of approximately six American scientists to visit the USSR after the death of Stalin. Marshak met the leaders of the Soviet Physics community, including Lev Landau. He made more trips to the USSR during the 1950s (US State Department debriefings after these trips are in the files), and became an acknowledged expert on Soviet science.
During the 1950s, Marshak established the "Rochester Conference", considered by his colleagues to be one of his most significant achievements. The conference evolved over the years into "The International Conference on High-Energy Physics." The Rochester Conference was instrumental in bringing together scientists from around the world, and served as a model for the establishment of international conferences in other fields. One of the most challenging aspects of the early conferences was the attempt to bring real Eastern European and Soviet physicists (as opposed to KGB agents) to the meetings. This effort required Marshak to carry out intense negotiations with the US State Department and with members of Congress. His other involvement in international science included participation in the establishment of the International Center of Theoretical Physics in Trieste, Italy, and the International Foundation for Science in Sweden.
Events at the University of Rochester received lots of publicity, and brought Marshak to the attention of the search committee looking for a new president for CCNY. They approached him with an offer to become president, just at a time when his social conscience had been roused. He accepted the offer and became CCNY President just at a time when the college was undergoing a vast change in demographics.
Typical of Marshak, he put his full effort into the struggle to redefine the college and bring it through these crises. In addition to improving the quality of several departments, he established important new programs such as the Biomedical Center and the Legal Center, raised the funds for a new performing arts center (the Leonard Davis Center), and pushed through the construction of a 150 million dollar academic complex. He also became involved in the debate about national educational policy and "Science and Public Policy", delivering many speeches on the subject. He also served on the board of directors for Harlem Hospital and for Colonial Penn Insurance Company. In the end, the success of his efforts was recognized by the naming of the 14-story science building on campus after him. The stress of his position at CCNY took a toll on his health, and he suffered a minor stroke during a confrontation with a student group. The stroke effected his balance for the remainder of his life.
After nine years at CCNY, his desire to return to physics led him to accept an offer as University Distinguished Professor at Virginia Tech, and he and Ruth moved to Blacksburg in 1979. During this period, he became President of the American Physical Society, the principle organization of physicists in the United States. Typical of his modus operandi, he took an activist approach to the job, using the weight of the society to debate the Reagan Administration on the issue of placing an anti-ballistic missile system into space, popularly known as "Star Wars."
Marshak officially retired as a professor at the age of 75. During the last five years of his life, he worked intensely on a book, entitled Conceptual Foundations of Modern Particle Physics. He finished the final corrections on the manuscript the day before he died. When he dropped the manuscript in the mailbox, he turn to his wife and said, in a joking voice, "It's done. Now I can die." The next day, December 23, 1992, he did. Minutes after the family convened in Cancun, Mexico, to celebrate Marshak's fiftieth wedding anniversary, he took the grandchildren down to the beach to enjoy the last hours of a sunny, windy afternoon. While the children played on the beach, he stepped into the warm water of the Gulf. The undertow was unexpectedly strong, and he apparently lost his balance. He fell into the water, couldn't stand up, and drowned.
A lengthy biography of Marshak is available on the Special Collections website: http://spec.lib.vt.edu/marshk/bio.htm.
Scope and Content
The collection consist of Marshak's files on the Shelter Island Conferences (1947-49) and his administrative and correspondence files on the Rochester Conferences on High-Energy Physics (1950-57), which he founded. After 1957 the conferences were held under the sponsorship of the International Union of Pure and Applied Physics (IUPAP) and Marshak's files from the conferences from 1958 to 1970 are also included. The collection also includes correspondence files on IUPAP (1953-73) and on the Commission on High Energy Physics (1958-63); photographs (1950-70); and a photocopy of an oral history interview done by Charles Weiner (1970).
The papers also includes correspondence, notes, reports, files, speech texts, newsclippings, autographs, photographs, transcripts, and other personalia donated in 1994. Topics include the national and international development of high-energy physics, meetings and symposia, and scientific committees; awards and prizes, administration and education, science in the Eastern Bloc and Third World, and the scientist as social activist or citizen-scientist.
Please note: The 1994 donation (materials in boxes other than Box 1-Box 5) is unprocessed. The "Contents List" below contains information from a paper inventory created in 1994, beginning with "Box A1." This is a working inventory and may not reflect all the contents of a particular box or folder. Materials were collection from multiple locations and are in their original order.
Arrangement
Materials in from the 1989 donation (Boxes 1-5) are arranged chronologically within subject files. The beginning of the "Contents List" below provides a detailed inventory of these boxes.
Materials from the 1994 donation are unprocessed, but the "Contents List" below contains information from a paper inventory created in 1994, beginning with "Box A1." Please note: This is a working inventory and may not reflect all the contents of a particular box or folder. Materials were collection from multiple locations and are in their original order.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
International Conference on High Energy Physics.; Rochester Conference on High Energy Nuclear Physics.
Subjects:
Physics; Soviet Union--Foreign relations--United States; Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Genre and Form Terms:
Correspondence; Proceedings
Local Subjects:
Science and Technology; Faculty; University Archives
Contents List
- Shelter Island Conferences on the Foundations of Quantum Mechanics, 1947-1949.
  - Correspondence from J. Robert Oppenheimer. (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Photograph of the 1947 conference. (Box-folder 1-2)
- University of Rochester High Energy Physics Conference. Rochester, New York, December 6, 1950.
  - Institutional sponsorship. (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Invitations. Correspondence. (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Attendees--lists. (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Scientific program. (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Administration. (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Post-conference tour. (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Post-conference correspondence--thank-you letters. (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Public relations. (Box-folder 1-10)
  - Manuscript proceedings and notes. (Box-folder 1-11)
- Second Annual Rochester Conference on Meson Physics. Rochester, New York, January 11-12, 1952.
  - Invitations. Correspondence. (Box-folder 1-12)
  - Attendees--lists. (Box-folder 1-13)
  - Scientific program. (Box-folder 1-14)
  - Administration. (Box-folder 1-15)
  - Public events. (Box-folder 1-16)
  - Post-conference correspondence--proceedings. Other correspondence. (Box-folder 1-17)
  - Distribution list for proceedings. (Box-folder 1-18)
  - Public relations. (Box-folder 1-19)
  - Printed proceedings. (Box-folder 1-20)
  - Photographs. (Box-folder 1-21)
- Third Annual Rochester Conference on High Energy Nuclear Physics. Rochester, New York, December 18-20, 1952.
  - Institutional sponsorship--National Science Foundation. (Box-folder 1-22)
  - Invitations. Correspondence. (Box-folder 1-23)
  - Attendees--lists. (Box-folder 1-24)
  - Administration. Budget. (Box-folder 1-25)
  - Administration. Lodging and transportation. (Box-folder 1-26)
  - Administration. Travel reimbursements. (Box-folder 1-27)
  - Scientific program. (Box-folder 1-28)
  - Public events. (Box-folder 1-29)
  - Post-conference correspondence. (Box-folder 1-30)
  - Sociological matters. (Box-folder 1-31)
  - Public relations. Correspondence. (Box-folder 1-32)
  - Public relations. Lists of countries represented, Nobel Laureates, etc. (Box-folder 1-33)
  - Printed proceedings. (Box-folder 1-34)
  - Photographs. (Box-folder 1-35)
- Fourth Annual Rochester Conference on High Energy Nuclear Physics. Rochester, New York, January 25-27, 1954.
  - Institutional sponsorship--National Science Foundation. (Box-folder 1-36)
  - Invitations. United States. Correspondence. (Box-folder 1-37)
  - Invitations. United States invitees--lists. (Box-folder 1-38)
  - Invitations. Foreign. Correspondence. (Box-folder 1-39)
  - Invitations. Foreign invitees--lists. (Box-folder 1-40)
  - Scientific program. (Box-folder 1-41)
  - Administration. Budget. (Box-folder 1-42)
  - Administration. Lodging and transportation arrangements. Lists. (Box-folder 1-43)
  - Administration. Lodging and travel arrangement requests. (Box-folder 1-44)
  - Administration. Local arrangements. Correspondence. (Box-folder 1-45)
  - Public events--banquet and social program. (Box-folder 1-46)
  - Post-conference correspondence--conference proceedings. (Box-folder 1-47)
  - Sociological matters. (Box-folder 1-48)
  - Public relations. (Box-folder 1-49)
  - Printed proceedings. (Box-folder 1-50)
- Fifth Annual Rochester Conference on High Energy Nuclear Physics. Rochester, New York, January 31-February 2, 1955.
  - Institutional sponsorship. (Box-folder 1-51)
  - Invitations. United States invitations. (Box-folder 1-52)
  - Invitations. Foreign invitations. (Box-folder 1-53)
  - Invitations. Invitees--lists and notes. (Box-folder 1-54)
  - Scientific Program. (Box-folder 1-55)
  - Administration. Reservations. (Box-folder 1-56)
  - Administration. Women's program. (Box-folder 1-57)
  - Public events, including banquet. (Box-folder 1-58)
  - Post-conference correspondence. (Box-folder 1-59)
  - Sociological matters. (Box-folder 1-60)
  - Public relations. Correspondence. (Box-folder 1-61)
  - Public relations. Newspaper and magazine articles. (Box-folder 1-62)
  - Printed proceedings. (Box-folder 1-63)
  - Photographs. (Box-folder 1-64)
- Sixth Annual Rochester Conference on High Energy Nuclear Physics. Rochester, New York, April 3-7, 1956.
  - Institutional sponsorship. (Box-folder 2-1)
  - United States invitations. (Box-folder 2-2)
  - United States invitations--industrial representatives. (Box-folder 2-3)
  - United States invitations--lists. Includes lists of University of Rochester graduate students. (Box-folder 2-4)
  - Foreign invitations. (Box-folder 2-5)
  - Foreign invitations--lists. (Box-folder 2-6)
  - Scientific program. Advisory board, tentative programs. (Box-folder 2-7)
  - Scientific program. General correspondence. (Box-folder 2-8)
  - Scientific program. Tuesday morning session--notes and correspondence. (Box-folder 2-9)
  - Scientific program. Tuesday afternoon session--notes and correspondence. (Box-folder 2-10)
  - Scientific program. Wednesday afternoon session--notes and correspondence. (Box-folder 2-11)
  - Scientific program. Thursday morning session--notes and correspondence. (Box-folder 2-12)
  - Scientific program. Thursday afternoon session--notes and correspondence. (Box-folder 2-13)
  - Scientific program. Friday session--notes and correspondence. (Box-folder 2-14)
  - Scientific program. Saturday morning session--notes and correspondence. (Box-folder 2-15)
  - Scientific program. Saturday afternoon session--notes and correspondence. (Box-folder 2-16)
  - Administration. Advisory committee. (Box-folder 2-17)
  - Administration. Budget--general. (Box-folder 2-18)
  - Administration. Budget--travel costs. (Box-folder 2-19)
  - Administration. Local arrangements. (Box-folder 2-20)
  - Public events. (Box-folder 2-21)
  - Post-conference correspondence. General. (Box-folder 2-22)
  - Post-conference. Proceedings. (Box-folder 2-23)
  - Sociological matters. General, including MATS. (Box-folder 2-24)
  - Sociological matters. Visas. (Box-folder 2-25)
  - Sociological matters. Russian scientists. (Box-folder 2-26)
  - Public relations. General. (Box-folder 2-27)
  - Public relations. Television program. Everett M. Hafner correspondence. (Box-folder 2-28)
  - Public relations. Press releases. (Box-folder 2-29)
  - Public relations. Newspaper articles. (Box-folder 2-30)
  - Printed proceedings. (Box-folder 2-31)
  - Photographs. (Box-folder 2-32)
- Moscow Conference on High Energy Particles. Moscow, USSR, May 14-22, 1956.
  - Invitation-correspondence. (Box-folder 2-33)
  - Pre-conference correspondence. (Box-folder 2-34)
  - Passport and visa-correspondence. (Box-folder 2-35)
  - Atomic Energy Commission. (Box-folder 2-36)
  - National Science Foundation. (Box-folder 2-37)
  - Scientific program. (Box-folder 2-38)
  - US publicity. (Box-folder 2-39)
  - Post-conference correspondence. (Box-folder 2-40)
  - Impressions of Western scientists-Aage Bohr, RE Marshak, KH Panofsky, VF Weisskopf. (Box-folder 2-41)
  - Photographs. (Box-folder 2-42)
- Seventh Annual Rochester Conference on High Energy Nuclear Physics. Rochester, New York, April 15-19, 1957.
  - Institutional Sponsorship. Agencies. (Box-folder 2-43)
  - Institutional sponsorship. Industries. (Box-folder 2-44)
  - Invitations. United States. (Box-folder 2-45)
  - United States invitees-lists. (Box-folder 2-46)
  - Foreign invitations. (Box-folder 2-47)
  - Foreign invitees-lists. (Box-folder 2-48)
  - Scientific program. Correspondence. (Box-folder 2-49)
  - Scientific program. Program copies. (Box-folder 2-50)
  - Administration. Attendance lists. (Box-folder 2-51)
  - Administration. Advisory committee. (Box-folder 2-52)
  - Administration. International Union of Pure and Applied Physics. (Box-folder 2-53)
  - Administration. Local arrangements. (Box-folder 2-54)
  - Administration. Local transportation. (Box-folder 2-55)
  - Administration. Finances. (Box-folder 2-56)
  - Administration. Travel arrangements. (Box-folder 2-57)
  - Public events. Banquet. (Box-folder 2-58)
  - Public events. Panel. (Box-folder 2-59)
  - Public events. "The Press Meets the Scientist." Correspondence. (Box-folder 2-60)
  - Public events. "The Press Meets the Scientist." Press release, questions, transcript. (Box-folder 2-61)
  - Post-conference tour. Correspondence. (Box-folder 3-1)
  - Post-conference tour. Itineraries. (Box-folder 3-2)
  - Post-conference correspondence. General. (Box-folder 3-3)
  - Post-conference correspondence. Proceedings. (Box-folder 3-4)
  - Post-conference correspondence. Thank-you letters. (Box-folder 3-5)
  - Sociological matters. MATS. (Box-folder 3-6)
  - Sociological matters. Visas. (Box-folder 3-7)
  - Sociological matters. Russian and Eastern bloc scientists. (Box-folder 3-8)
  - Public relations. General. (Box-folder 3-9)
  - Public relations. News releases. (Box-folder 3-10)
  - Public relations. Newspaper articles. (Box-folder 3-11)
  - Printed proceedings. (Box-folder 3-12)
  - Photographs. (Box-folder 3-13)
- Eighth Annual International Conference on High Energy Physics. CERN, Geneva, Switzerland, June 27-July 5, 1958.
  - Advisory committee. (Box-folder 3-14)
  - Review committee. (Box-folder 3-15)
  - United States invitations. (Box-folder 3-16)
  - Scientific program. (Box-folder 3-17)
  - General correspondence. (Box-folder 3-18)
  - Photograph. (Box-folder 3-19)
- Ninth Annual International Conference on High Energy Physics. Kiev, USSR, July 15-25, 1959.
  - Invitations. Western invitees-Robert E. Marshak correspondence. (Box-folder 3-20)
  - Invitations. Western invitees-Robert E. Marshak and Wolfgang KH Panofsky joint correspondence. (Box-folder 3-21)
  - Invitations. Western invitees-Wolfgang KH Panofsky correspondence. (Box-folder 3-22)
  - Invitations. Western invitees-CJ Bakker correspondence. (Box-folder 3-23)
  - Invitations. Western invitees-Clifton T. McCleod correspondence. (Box-folder 3-24)
  - Invitations. American invitees-lists. (Box-folder 3-25)
  - Invitations. Lists of invitees by country, state. (Box-folder 3-26)
  - Scientific program. Correspondence. (Box-folder 3-27)
  - Scientific program. Program copies. (Box-folder 3-28)
  - Administration. General, including correspondence with Soviet scientists. (Box-folder 3-29)
  - Administration. Travel. (Box-folder 3-30)
  - Documents on Soviet science and scientific institutions. (Box-folder 3-31)
  - Public relations. General. Includes correspondence on a 1964 New York Times article by Marshak. (Box-folder 3-32)
  - Public relations. Requests for information. (Box-folder 3-33)
  - Proceedings- correspondence. (Box-folder 3-34)
  - Printed proceedings-volume 1. (Box-folder 3-35)
  - Printed proceedings-volume 2. (Box-folder 3-36)
  - Photographs. (Box-folder 3-37)
- Tenth International Conference on High Energy Physics. Rochester, New York, August 25-September 1, 1960.
  - Institutional and industrial sponsorship. General. (Box-folder 3-38)
  - Institutional and industrial sponsorship. Air Force Office of Scientific Research. (Box-folder 3-39)
  - Institutional and industrial sponsorship. Atomic Energy Commission. Includes PSAC, AEC report, "Explanatory Statement on Particle Physics and a Proposed Federal Program in Support of High Energy Accelerator Physics." (Box-folder 3-40)
  - Institutional and industrial sponsorship. IUPAP. (Box-folder 3-41)
  - Institutional and industrial sponsorship. National Academy of Science. (Box-folder 3-42)
  - Institutional and industrial sponsorship. National Science Foundation. (Box-folder 3-43)
  - Institutional and industrial sponsorship. Office of Naval Research. (Box-folder 3-44)
  - Institutional and industrial sponsorship. Office of Ordnance Research. (Box-folder 3-45)
  - Institutional and industrial sponsorship. Industry. (Box-folder 3-46)
  - Invitations. United States invitations. (Box-folder 3-47)
  - Foreign invitations. (Box-folder 3-48)
  - CERN invitees. (Box-folder 3-49)
  - Soviet and Eastern bloc invitations. (Box-folder 3-50)
  - Foreign invitees-lists. (Box-folder 3-51)
  - Invitations. Lists of participants. (Box-folder 3-52)